A Finding Aid to the Esphyr Slobodkina Papers in the Archives of American Art AAA.slobesph
Archives of American Art
Esphyr Slobodkina papers
circa 1925-1995
AAA.slobesph
Archives of American Art
1.7 Linear feet
The papers of painter, sculptor, author, and illustrator Esphyr Slobodkina measure 1.7 linear feet and date from circa 1925 to 1995. Found within the papers are personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Ilya Bolotowsky, George L.K. Morris, and Paul Kelpe; writings, including a copy of the autobiography Notes for a Biographer (vol. 1); printed materials; photographs; and material on the American Abstract Artists, including administrative records, business correspondence, and publications.
Bolotowsky, Ilya, 1907-1981
Slobodkina, Esphyr, 1908-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Esphyr Slobodkina donated a portion of her papers in 1970, and made additional multiple gifts between 1995 and 1996.
Separated Materials note
Originals of material loaned for microfilming, including a travel album, printed material, notes, McDowell colony correspondence, and an American Abstract Artists financial ledger, were returned to Slobodkina in 1970. Loaned material is available on reels N70-61, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid. Additionally, 69 rolled drawings on tracing paper were transferred to Hillwood Art Museum in 2006.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives also holds the American Abstract Artists records.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels N70-54 and N70-55 at the Archives of American Art offices and affliate research centers. The film is also available for interlibrary library loan but researchers should note that the film is incomplete and the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter, sculptor, author, and illustrator Esphyr Slobodkina (1908-2002) lived and worked in New York City, Great Neck, and Long Island, New York and was known for her abstract art and her children’s books, including the seminal Caps For Sale.
Slobodkina was born in Chelyabinsk, Siberia to Solomon Slobodkin and his wife, Itta Agranovich. After the Russian Revolution and Civil War of 1917-1918, her family immigrated to Harbin, Manchuria where her father found work with Standard Oil and her mother contributed to the family’s finances by working as a dressmaker. After graduating from high school in 1927, Slobodkina immigrated to the United States to join her brother in New York City where she enrolled at the National Academy of Design.
At the Academy, Slobodkina met her future husband, the artist and fellow Russian émigré Ilya Bolotowsky. In 1936, they became founding members of the American Abstract Artists, an artist run organization that worked to advance abstract art at a time when few opportunities to exhibit their works existed. She served as the organization’s first secretary and later served as treasurer, president, and institutional bibliographer.
In 1937, Slobodkina met the children’s author Margaret Wise Brown. After seeing her work, Brown invited Slobodkina to illustrate The Little Fireman, the first of their many collaborations together. In 1940, Slobodkina’s first published book, Caps For Sale, was released and has remained in print for over 70 years. It won the Lewis Carroll Shelf Award in 1958 and is considered a classic of children’s literature.
Slobodkina and Bolotowsky divorced in 1938, after which she continued to produce abstract mixed media paintings and sculptures. Her first major one-person show was organized by the gallery owner A.E. Gallatin in 1940. Through the 1940s and into 1970s, Slobodkina regularly contributed to group exhibitions and her works are owned by numerous institutions, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Whitney Museum, Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and Hillwood Art Museum.
In addition to publishing children’s books, Slobodkina authored three volumes of her autobiography, Notes for a Biographer (1976-1983) and edited American Abstract Artists: Its Publications, Catalogs, and Membership (1979) and the folio Ilya Bolotwosky (1985). Active until the end of her life, she oversaw the production of musical audio recordings for her 20 children’s books well into her 80s, and at the age of 90, designed a museum financed through the Slobodkina Foundation. She died at her home in Glen Head, Long Island in 2002.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, sculptor, author, and illustrator Esphyr Slobodkina measure 1.7 linear feet and date from circa 1925 to 1995. Found within the papers are personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Ilya Bolotowsky, George L.K. Morris, and Paul Kelpe; writings, including a copy of the autobiography Notes for a Biographer (vol. 1); printed materials; photographs; and material on the American Abstract Artists, including administrative records, business correspondence, and publications.
Correspondence is primarily with Slobodkina’s family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from her first husband, Ilya Bolotowsky, as well as abstract artists George L.K. Morris, Paul Kelpe, Ruth Eckstein, Leo Rabkin, and Harry Tedlie. The series also includes correspondence regarding her published works.
Writings consist of 3 essays by Slobodkina on abstract art, the autobiography Notes for a Biographer (vol. 1), the edited folio Ilya Bolotowsky, and a small notebook kept by Ilya Bolotowsky during the 1920s-30s.
Printed material includes clippings; samples of announcements and cards designed by Slobodkina; exhibition announcements and catalogs; and press releases.
Photographs are of Slobodkina and her paintings and sculptures, as well as photographs of artwork by other abstract artists.
American Abstract Artists' records includes administrative material, correspondence, writings, selected exhibitions, and printed material dating from 1936 to 1996.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1934-1992 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1920-1985 (6 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed material, circa 1939-1994 (7 folders; Box 1, OV 4)
Series 4: Photographs, circa 1925-1970 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: American Abstract Artists, circa 1936-1995 (0.9 linear feet, Box 1-3, OV 4)
American Abstract Artists; Eckstein, Ruth, 1916-; Kelpe, Paul, 1902-1985; Morris, George L. K. 1905-1975; Rabkin, Leo; Tedlie, Harry; Authors -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State); Painters -- New York (State); Painting, Abstract -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State); Women artists--New York
- Correspondence, 1934-1992; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence is primarily with Slobodkina’s family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from her first husband, Ilya Bolotowsky, as well as abstract artists George L.K. Morris, Paul Kelpe, Ruth Eckstein, Leo Rabkin, and Harry Tedlie. The series also includes correspondence regarding her publications, including her children’s books, the folio on Ilya Bolotowsky, and Slobodkina’s autobiography.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, then followed by correspondence related to Slobodkina’s book projects.
  - A-Z, Miscellaneous, 1940-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bolotowsky, Ilya, 1934-1947, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    For typescripts of handwritten letters and English transcriptions of letters written in Russian, see Box 1, Folder 33.
  - Eckstein, Ruth, circa 1965-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Forest Lake School, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gallatin, A.E., 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hulbeck, Beate, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kelly, Isabel, circa 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kelpe, Paul, circa 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mason, Alice Trumbull, 1942-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meierhaus, Joe, 1942-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Morris, George and Suzy Frelinghuysen, 1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Nieuwe Kerk Museum, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rabkin, Leo, circa 1970-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sennhauser, John, 1949-1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Shaw, Charles G., circa 1940-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Slobodkina, Esphyr, circa 1960-1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Tedlie, Harry, circa 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Washburn Gallery, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Publication of Children's Books, 1974, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Publication of Ilya Bolotowsky, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Receipt of Notes for a Biographer, Friends, 1977, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Receipt of Notes for a Biographer, Institutions, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters and Inscriptions to Recipients of Unidentified Book, circa 1960-1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1940-1990 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings, circa 1920-1985; Series 2; 6 Folders Box 1
  Writings include 3 essays by Slobodkina on abstract art, the autobiography Notes for a Biographer (vol. 1), the edited folio Ilya Bolotowsky, and a small notebook kept by Ilya Bolotowsky during the 1920s-30s. The folio reprints a selection of Bolotowsky’s drawings and his correspondence to Slobodkina during their marriage, which are typescript and translated from Russian.
  Materials are arranged by author, then by document type.
  - Slobodkina, Esphyr, Notes for a Biographer (Part I), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Slobodkina, Esphyr, "My Secret Life With George Morris", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Slobodkina, Esphyr, "Small Abstract Line Drawing", circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Slobodkina, Esphyr, "What is Abstract Art?", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Slobodkina, Esphyr (folio editor), Ilya Bolotowsky, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    For original letters, see Box 1, Folder 2.
  - Bolotowsky, Ilya, Notebook, circa 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, circa 1939-1994; Series 3; 7 Folders Box 1, OV 4
  Printed material consists of clippings; samples of announcements, cards, and brochures designed by Slobodkina; exhibition announcements and catalogs; press releases, and miscellaneous printed material.
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Clippings, circa 1939-1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Oversized material housed in OV 4.
  - Designs by Esphyr Slobodkina, circa 1955-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950-1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, 1961-1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, Group Shows, 1984-1991 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Postcard, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Press Releases, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Oversized Clipping, circa 1936-1970 (Box OV 4)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 35.
- Photographs, circa 1925-1970; Series 4; 3 Folders Box 1
  Photographs are of Slobodkina and her paintings and sculptures, as well as photographs of artwork by other abstract artists.
  Materials are arranged by subject matter.
  - Photographs of Esphyr Slobodkina, circa 1925-1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Esphyr Slobodkina, circa 1940-1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, circa 1938-1965 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- American Abstract Artists, circa 1936-1995; Series 5; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1-3, OV 4
  The series American Abstract Artists includes administrative material, correspondence, writings, selected exhibitions, and printed material.
  Administrative material includes copies of the constitution, meeting minutes, membership lists, and a treasurer’s report. Correspondence is with officers of the AAA regarding meetings, member dues, and publication projects. Writings include three essays on the AAA and draft copies of American Abstract Artists, 1936-1966. Exhibitions include substantial correspondence regarding the logistics of two early exhibitions, the “National Exhibition” (1940/1940-1941) and the “Traveling Exhibition of Matted Works” (1940-1941). Printed material contains clippings; exhibition announcements, catalogs, and posters; sample organizational letterhead; and a copy of American Abstract Artists: Its Publications, Catalogs, and Membership.
  Administrative materials, writings, and printed materials are arranged by document type. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, then followed by correspondence related to book projects. Exhibitions are arranged alphabetically by exhibition title.
  The series is arranged as 5 subseries.
  5.1: Administrative materials, 1949-1995
  5.2: Correspondence, 1940-1995
  5.3: Writings, circa 1936-1994
  5.4: Exhibitions, 1939-1966
  5.5: Printed Material, 1936-1992
  - Administrative Material, 1949-1995; 5.1
    - Constitution, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1949-1995 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
    - Membership Lists, 1958-1991 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1965-1982 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1995; 5.2
    - A-Z Miscellaneous, 1940-1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Goodyear, John, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Kelpe, Paul, circa 1956-1965 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Mason, Alice, 1949-1962 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Rabkin, Leo, 1961-1979 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Riese, Beatrice, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Rousseau, Irene, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - University of New Mexico, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Membership Dues, circa 1961-1978 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Publication of American Abstract Artists, 1936-1966, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Requests for American Abstract Artists: Its Publications, Catalogs, and Memberships, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Writings, circa 1936-1994; 5.3
    - Book Draft, American Abstract Artists, 1936-1966, circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
    - Slobodkina, Esphyr, On American Abstract Artists and Art, circa 1960-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Slobodkina, Esphyr, "Historical Outline", circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Unknown Author, "Pioneers in the Field", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notes, circa 1936-1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Exhibitions, 1939-1966; 5.4
    - "28th Annual Exhibition" (1964), circa 1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "American Abstract Artists, 1936-1986" (1986), 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Exhibition in Honor of Albers, Morris, Rice-Pereira, and Shaw" (1976) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "National Exhibition" (1940), Administrative Memorandum, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "National Exhibition" (1940), Lehigh University, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "National Exhibition" (1940), University of Minnesota, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "National Exhibition" (1940), Declines to Exhibit, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "National Exhibition" (1940-1941), Declines to Exhibit (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Riverside Museum Show" (1966), circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Traveling Exhibition of Matted Works" (1940-1941), Administrative Memorandum (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Traveling Exhibition of Matted Works" (1940-1941), Cranbrook Academy of Art (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Traveling Exhibition of Matted Works" (1940-1941), Norfolk Museum (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Traveling Exhibition of Matted Works" (1940-1941), Declines to Exhibit (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Printed Material, 1936-1992; 5.5
    - Book, American Abstract Artists: Its Publications, Catalogs, and Membership, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Book Draft, American Abstract Artists: Its Publications, Catalogs, and Membership, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Clippings, 1936-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
    - Exhibition Posters, 1956-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Letterhead, circa 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Newsletters, circa 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Press Releases, 1972-1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Oversized Exhibition Posters, 1956-1982 (Box OV 4)
      Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 8.